Guide to the Conrad Moricand Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Conrad Moricand papers
1909-1957
1947-1953
GEN MSS 1152
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.84
(4 boxes)
Moricand, Conrad, 1887-1954
Scope and Contents
The Conrad Moricand Papers contain correspondence, 1915-1956 and undated, including two brief letters to Moricand from Henry Miller, 1938, and letters to Moricand from Théophile Briant, 1948, and Georges Oltramare, 1947-1953, from Miller to Briant, 1956, from Hermann, Graf von Keyserling, to Miller, 1938, and from O. V. de L. Milosz to Nicolas Beauduin, with poems by Beauduin, 1916-1937; writings by Moricand, including a memoir, "Les philistines (U. S. A., 1948)," typescript carbon, undated, a revised proof for Les traces du culte d'Isis (Paramé: Éditions du Goéland, 1952), and autograph manuscript notes about Henry Miller, Anaïs Nin, and others; autograph manuscript poems by René Guy Cadou and Jacques Dyssord, undated; engravings by Francis Picabia, undated; autograph books kept by Moricand in France, with signatures and addresses of authors, artists, musicians, and others, 1928-1931; clippings and other printed material, 1935-1957, some relating to Le Goéland, a literary journal edited by Théophile Briant; passports and other identification documents, 1909-1947 and undated; and documents relating to travel to the United States, 1947.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michel Fabre on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Conrad Moricand (1887-1954)
Conrad Moricand, French astrologer and author; also used the name Claude Valence. Moricand lived with American author Henry Miller in Big Sur, California, in 1948, and was the subject of Miller's memoir A Devil in Paradise ([New York]: The New American Library, [1956]), also published in Miller's Big Sur and the Oranges of Hieronymus Bosch (New York: New Directions, 1957).
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1915-1956. Series II. Writings, 1952 and undated. III. Writings and Visual Materials by Others, 1950 and undated. IV. Other Papers, 1909-1957.
Goéland; Astrologers -- France; Astrology -- France; Occultism -- France; California -- Description and travel; Lithographs -- France -- 20th Century; Astrologers -- France -- 20th Century; Beauduin, Nicolas, 1880-1960; Briant, Théophile; Cadou, René Guy; Dyssord, Jacques, 1880-1952; Keyserling, Hermann, Graf von, 1880-1946; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980 ( Devil in paradise); Miller, Henry, 1891-1980 -- Friends and associates; Milosz, O. V. de L. (Oscar Vladislas de Lubicz), 1877-1939; Moricand, Conrad, 1887-1954; Nin, Anaïs, 1903-1977; Oltramare, Georges, 1896-1960; Picabia, Francis, 1879-1953
- Correspondence, 1915-1956, undated; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Letters to Moricand, unless otherwise noted.
  - Bachelard, Gaston, 1952 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birmann, [S.?], 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Briant, Théophile (from Moricand), 1948 January-April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Borle, Walter, 1948 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Keyserling, Hermann, Graf von (to Henry Miller), 1938 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miller, Henry, 1938 October-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miller, Henry (to Théophile Briant), 1956 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Milosz, O. V. de L. (Oscar Vladislas de Lubicz) (to Nicolas Beauduin, with poems by Beauduin), 1916-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mondzain, Simon, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oltramare, Georges (with poems by Oltramare, and clippings and third-party correspondence about him), 1946-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Perlès, Alfred, 1947 November-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Picabia, Francis, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Relles, Dominique Birmann de (with poems by Relles), 1952-195[3?], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wright, Sally, 1947 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Max", 1947 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Writings, 1952, undated; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  - "Les philistines (U. S. A., 1948)" (memoir). Typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Les traces du culte d'Isis (Paramé: Éditions du Goéland). Proof, revised, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Notes (autograph manuscript)
    - Miller, Henry, undated; 6 (Box 2, Folder 18-23)
    - Nin, Anaïs, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
- Writings and Visual Materials by Others, 1950, undated; Series III; 6
  - Cadou, René Guy. "Dans le train bleu" (poem). Autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dyssord, Jacques. Poems. Autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Picabia, Francis. Lithographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Picabia, Francis. Paintings (photographs by Georges Allie), undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Roederer, Claude. Untitled engraving, 1950 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 38)
  - Unidentified. Photograph of an unidentified woman ("Picabia assistant"), undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Other Papers, 1909-1957, undated; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Autograph book, 1928 October-1929 May (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Autograph book, 1929 May-1931 June (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Clippings, 1935-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Drawing by Moricand, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Passports and other identification documents, 1909-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Travel documents, 1947 October-December (Box 3, Folder 37)